<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-10T19:57:43+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A Slippery Slope</title><subtitle>A Blog About Some Adventures</subtitle><author><name>Tyler Abbot</name></author><entry><title type="html">Goulotte Chere</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/12/31/chere.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goulotte Chere" /><published>2025-12-31T23:45:13+01:00</published><updated>2025-12-31T23:45:13+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/12/31/chere</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/12/31/chere.html"><![CDATA[<p>A new year's eve gully with a speed run of the Vallee Blanche.</p>

<p>In December we hosted some of my family for Christmas. It was awesome to show them around Chamonix, we even took them on a walk to the Col des Flambeaux off of the Skyway. However, after three weeks without climbing I was getting antsy. I hit up my regular climbing partner, but he'd suffered a terrible setback: he got a job. So I turned to outdoor Tinder (aka <a href="http://getoak.app/">Oak</a>). As usual I quickly found an Englishman, Jack, who properly sandbags their ability and who was down for a day out. We decided to head for the Goulotte Chere on new year's eve as a nice warm up for the winter climbing season.</p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/chere.jpg" alt="Tacul North East Face">
<span class="caption text-muted">The Goulottee Chere climbs the right most gully on the north east face of the Mont Blanc du Tacul.</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">The Climb</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://www.camptocamp.org/routes/54159/fr/triangle-du-tacul-goulotte-chere">Chere</a> is a classic in Chamonix. First climbed in 1973, it has easy access from the Aiguille de Midi cable car and is pretty introductory, going at M3 with a crux of 85 degree ice. The route climbs the north east face of the Mont Blanc du Tacul, also known as the Triangle du Tacul.</p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/crampons.jpg" alt="The Tunnel">
<span class="caption text-muted">Putting on our crampons before the Midi ridge.</span>

<p>The day started off with a few hiccups (as usual), but more or less on time. The day before I'd driven to Cham to be sure we had tickets for the first lift, then on my way to the lift in the morning I realized I'd forgotten them. A usually 30 minute drive turned into an hour fifteen and I was definitely not early. But, we were only one cable car late so no big deal. I quickly realized Jack was better than he let on when he said he was a tree surgeon (a funny british term for arborist and which means he spends his days juggling chainsaws while hanging off a rope) who was working his way through the BMC guide prereqs just for fun. So he could be the rope gun for the day. We split up our gear a bit and headed out onto the Midi ridge, which always makes me want to shit my pants a little bit.</p>


<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/ridge.jpg" alt="Midi Ridge">
<span class="caption text-muted">Coming down the steepest part of the Midi ridge</span>

<p>To get from the Midi cable car station to the glacier you have to descend a very exposed snow ridge. In the winter the Compagnie de Mont Blanc installs fixed ropes and the ridge is supposed to be pretty chill, but I've only ever done it in summer when the snow is loose and it is crowded with people pushing past eachother. Since an unarrested fall would mean tumbling 1000m to the Plan de l'Aiguille, it's not the most comfortable. Luckily, this time there were solid steps and the snow was like concrete, so it was pretty calm. At the base of the ridge we put our skis on to head for the climb.</p>


<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/skis.jpg" alt="Skis On">
<span class="caption text-muted">Jack with his skis, the Triangle du Tacul and our route in the background.</span>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/approach.jpg" alt="Skinning">
<span class="caption text-muted">Skinning towards the Triangle du Tacul</span>

<p>We skinned across the glacier at a leisurly pace, having seen three parties ahead of us already. When we got to the base, we decided to skin past two parties and try to cut the line, but we weren't quite fast enough getting racked up and the others headed off ahead of us. We were discussing our options for heading home as well. We were keen for the Vallee Blanche and I had never done it, so was excited to try. The Vallee Blanche is a famous off piste ski run that descends 2800m and travels 17km over glaciated terrain, so I was a bit worried about time. Jack claimed it could be done in 30 minutes and I laughed, suggesting more like an hour 30... This would come back to bite us later.</p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/base.jpg" alt="Base">
<span class="caption text-muted">Looking up at the climb with our neighbors ahead of us.</span>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/topout.jpg" alt="Jack Topping Out">
<span class="caption text-muted">Jack topping out the last technical section before we rappelled off.</span>

<p>I was feeling shit from the altitude so suggested Jack take the first lead. He said he hated passing peopl on routes, that it wasn't very English, so I figured we would remain in the rear. However as he reached the first belay he blew past two teams and headed up. I couldn't have been happier. On this kind of route the most dangerous thing is other climbers who could knock rocks and ice down on you. We simul climbed the first two pitches to the crux. I was still feeling terrible so asked Jack to take the lead again. He cruised through and I lead the last pitch. As we rapelled past the team below us I managed to catch a nice picture of a nice young Belgian. I promised to share it with him at the base, but didn't realize how big of a rush we'd be in...</p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/belgian.jpg" alt="A Belgian">
<span class="caption text-muted">A very nice Belgian kid in the pair behind us, on the last techinical ice section.</span>

<h2 class="section-heading">The Descent</h2>

<p>Now that we were at the base, we realized we were in a pickle. It was 3:15 and we had two choices: skin back the Aiguille de Midi for the last lift down at 4:30 or descend the Vallee Blanche to try to catch the train from Montenvers, but the last lift from the glacier to the train station was at 4:00. Neither option looked good, as crossing back to the midi can be slow, but in hindsight we would have probably made it. However, we decided on the Vallee Blanche and I would soon regret it. As we skied away we wagered the Belgians would be spending New Year's even in the bathrooms at the midi, a right of passage here apparently. I'm hoping never to have to experience it!</p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/valleeblanche.jpg" alt="The Verte">
<span class="caption text-muted">The Aiguille Verte from the Vallee Blanche, just under the Gros Rognon.</span>

<p>From the base of the climb we had to ski across a flat expanse that must be at least a kilometer or more. You can get your speed up initially and try to just cruise across. However, the snow on the flat bit had been wind effected for weeks without new snow and was covered in enormous sastrugi (anvil shaped blocks of snow). So as I skied across, every few feet I had to ski over a 12 inch high ridge of snow, trying not to lose speed, all this for five to ten minutes straight. Then we descended the right side of the Gros Rognon, the snow now at 25-30 degrees and still covered in sastrugis. By the time I caught up to Jack at the base of the slope, it had been just a few minutes of skiing and my quads were shot... I was in trouble.</p>

<p>We continued to descend and Jack navigated as best he could. The low snow cover meant there were crevasses everywhere and lots of exposed rock. I'd learned he'd grown up nearby and his brother was a ski instructor, so he was cruising. If it weren't for that I would have been hosed, as it was all I could do not to stop for breaks to rest my legs. The snow conditions were better now, but the first 10 minutes had wasted my quads, not to mention I'd skipped lunch. I stared to cramp up completely but we had to keep moving. We continued on and eventually we arrived at the most technical bit, descending from the Glacier du Geant to the Mer de Glace. Finally Jack admitted, "I don't think I've ever skied it this dry." Phew! It wasn't jsut me who thought the lack of snow and rocks everywhere was a bit surprising.</p>

<p>We had a bit of a discussion and admitted we most likely wouldn't make it to the lift. However, it was getting dark and if we didn't make it to the Mer de Glace before dark we would be unable to navigate the crevasses and would face an open bivy here on the glacier. So we carried on. I didn't have time to take pictures or look around to appreciate the scenery, I just focused on the cramps in my legs and keeping up with Jack.</p>

<p>Eventually, we made it through the toughest bit and Jack was optimistic that if we rounded the next bend the lift staff would see us and wait. So we headed off across a flat bit of the glacier, probably 2-3 kilometers long. This was probably the hardest skiing of my life! It was maybe 5 degrees of slope, but my quads were completely cramped up and I couldn't stop. I just tried to remember Kelly Cordes' mantra of "suffer well", although here I was skiing a green run with some cramps, not as tough as Kelly.</p>

<p>At one point I fell down and was so tired I couldn't stand back up, I had to take my skis off, stand up, and put them back on. The last two kilometers were through a narrow band of snow weaving through rocks. At many points the snow was cut through by a boulder or rock, but I was too tired to try to avoid it. As of writing I still haven't looked at my ski bases, I'm too scared of what I'll see. Jack managed to make it to the lift station a good 5-10 minutes before me and convince the staff to wait. As I struggled to find my way to the base of the stairs he would yell some encouragement: "Don't stop moving!" Climbing the stairs should have felt easy, but I could barely do it, grunting and groaning up each step. When we finally sat down in the cable car I honestly couldn't believe we'd made it.</p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/eod.jpg" alt="The End">
<span class="caption text-muted">Trying to look less hagard than I felt while waiting for the Montenvers train.</span>

There were quite a few tourists waiting for the train as well, but no one else had pushed any mountain adventures as late as us. We caught the train after having a few snacks and talking about how crazy it was we'd made it.

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/20251231/train.jpg" alt="The Train">
<span class="caption text-muted">Jack enjoying the views from the train on the way back to Chamonix.</span>

Overall it was a really great way to end the year. I can't say I would do the ski again, but do not regret it in the least! I can't wait to do the Vallee Blanche again, but instead of 45 minutes, to take a few hours to properly enjoy it.]]></content><author><name>Tyler Abbot</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A new year's eve gully with a speed run of the Vallee Blanche.]]></summary></entry></feed>